[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net SC radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
software the more AI models you use the
harder it is to match the right tool to
the task at hand you can do that
automatically with code gate Multiplex
small specialized models and large
heroic models so that every prompt is
sent to the model that minimizes your
costs and maximizes your results Cod
gate is open source learn more at COD
gate. a that's c d g a te.
a welcome to software engineering radio
I'm your host Bri shanut today I will be
discussing small language models with
sonil Malia sonel is a co-founder and
CTO of flip AI prior to this sunel was
the head of AWS NLP service comprehend
and helped start AWS bedro he's the
co-creator of AWS deep racer he has over
25 patents filed in the area of machine
learning reinforcement learning and LP
and distributed systems sunel welcome to
software engineering radio thank you
bries so happy to be here and talk about
this topic that's near and dear to me we
have covered language models in some of
our prior episodes notably episode 648
611 610 and 582 let's start off sunel
maybe by explaining what small language
models are and how they differ from
large language models or llms yeah this
is a very interesting question because
you know the term itself is sort of time
bound because what is large today can
mean something else tomorrow as the
underlying Hardwares get better and
bigger so you know if I go back in time
it's around 2020 that's when the llm
term starts to sort of emerge with the
Advent of people building like billion
parameter models and quickly after open
AI releases gpt3 which is like a 175
billion parameter model that sort of
becomes like this gold standard of what
a true llm means but the number keeps
changing right so I'd like to Define
slms in a more a slightly different way
not in terms of number of parameters but
in terms of like practical terms so what
that means is you know something that
you can run with resources that are
easily accessible you're not like
constrained by GPU availability or you
need the biggest GPU the best GPU you
know I think to distill all of this I'd
say as of today early 2025 a 10 billion
parameter model that's operating with
like say a Max of like 10K context
length which means that you can give it
like an input of around 10K words
maximum but where the inference latency
is around 1 second so it's pretty fast
overall right like so I would Define
slms in that context which is a lot more
practical makes sense and I believe you
know as the models become more memory
intensive the definition itself will
change I believe when I was reading of
GPT 4 actually has about 1.76 trillion
parameters yeah that actually you know
some of these close Source models are
very hard when people talk about numbers
because what can happen is people you
know nowadays use like a mixture of
expert architecture
model what that means is they'll sort of
put together like a really large model
that has specialized parts to it again
I'm trying to explain in very easy
language here what that means is when
you run inference through these models
not all the parameters are activated so
you don't necessarily need 1.7 trillion
parameters worth of compute to actually
run the models so you end up using some
percentage of that that actually makes
it a little interesting when we say like
oh how big the model is but like you
want to actually talk about like number
of active parameters because that really
defines the underlying hardware and
resources you need so if we go back
again something like gpt3 when we when I
say 175 billion parameters all the 175
billion parameters are involved in
giving you that final answer right so if
I understood that correctly only a
subset of the parameters would be used
for the inference in any particular use
case in mixture of expert model model in
that architecture and that's a very
popular for the last maybe a year and a
half has been a popular sort of way for
people to build and train because
training these really really large
models is extremely hard but training
like mixture of experts which are sort
of collection of smaller models
relatively smaller models are much
easier and then you put them together so
to speak that's a emerging Trend even
today very popular and a very prag atic
way of actually going forward in
training and then running inference okay
and what differentiates an slm from an
expert model or are they the same yeah
I'd say how we've actually ended up
training llms being general purpose
models like because these models are
trained on internet Corpus and whatever
data you could get you know hand so by
the nature of like when you look at
internet internet has all the sort of
topics on the world that you can think
about and that actually finds the
characteristics of the model so hence
you would characterize them as general
purpose large language models expert
models are when you know model has a
certain expertise or like you don't care
about let's say You're Building A coding
model which is an expert coding model
you don't necessarily care about it
knowing anything about Napoleon or
anything to do with history because
that's irrelevant to the conversation or
the topic of choice so expert models are
something that are focused on one or two
areas and go really deep and slms are
the term being just smaller language
model from a size and practicality
perspective but typically when you think
about what people end up doing is you're
saying that hey I don't care about
history so I only need this little part
of the model or I just need the model to
be expert in only one thing so I let me
train a smaller model which is focused
on just one topic and then it becomes an
expert so they're interchangeable in
some respect but it needn't be right I
just want to Deep dive into the
differences and attributes between slms
and llms before we go into the details
I'd like you to Define what a parameter
is in the context of a language model so
let's talk about this actually comes
from if we go background the whole
concept of neural Nets and early days we
call them neural Nets they're modeled on
the biological brain and how I guess the
animal nervous system and brain
functions so the fundamental unit is a
neuron and neuron actually has a self
has some sort of memory some sort of
specialization the neuron connects to
many other neurons to form your entire
brain and certain responses based on
stimuli like certain other sets of
neurons sort of activate and give you
sort of the final response that's sort
of what is modeled so a parameter like
you can sort of think about it as
equivalent to like a neuron or a compute
unit and then these parameters come
together to sort of synthesize the final
response for you again I'm giving a very
high level answer here that what
translates to from a practical point of
view right like when when I say 10
billion parameters or model that roughly
translates into X number of gigabytes
and there's a I would say there a
approximate formula and you know it
depends on the Precision that you want
to use to represent your data so if you
take about like a 32-bit representation
floating bit that's about four bytes of
data so you multiply 10 into 4 that is
40 gigs of memory that you need to store
these parameters in order to make them
functional and of course you can go half
Precision right and then you're suddenly
looking at only 20 gigs of memory to
serve that 10 billion parameter model
that's a very good example comparing it
to neurons it brings to life what
parameters are and why it's important in
the context of language models yeah it's
actually the origin itself like how
people actually thought about this in
the ' 50s and how they modeled and how
this finally evolved so rather than it
being an example I would say people went
and modeled real life neurons to finally
come up with the terminology and how the
design of these things and to this day
people sort of compare everything to
rationalizing reasoning understanding
Etc very human like Concepts into how
these llms behave right how does the
computational footprint of an slm
compared to that with an llm yeah so
computational footprint is directly
proportional to the size so size is the
number one driver of the footprint sort
of like I would say maybe like 90% the
rest of the 10% will be something like
you know how long is your input sequence
and these models typically have a
certain like maximum range back in the
day I would say like 1,000 to tokens or
roughly tokens a definition of let me
sort of go a little segue into how these
models actually work because I think
that may be relevant as we dive in so
these language models right they're
essentially a prediction system the
output of the language model for you
when you go to chat GPT or anywhere else
like it you know it's giving you
beautiful blogs and sentences and so on
but the model doesn't necessarily say
understand sentences as a whole it
actually understands parts of it it is
actually made up of words and
technically sub wordss subwords are what
we call as tokens and the idea here is
the model actually predicts a
probability distribution on these
subword tokens that allows it to say hey
the next word should be with
99% probability should be this and then
you take the collection of the last n
words you predicted and then you predict
the next word n plus one word and so on
it's Auto regressive in nature so this
is how these language models work so the
token length as in how many words if
you're predicting over 100 words versus
10,000 words is a material difference
because now you have to take when you're
predicting the 10,000th word you have to
take all the
9999 words that you have previously as
context into that model right like so
that actually has a sort of a nonlinear
scaling effect on how you end up
predicting your final output so that
along with the fundamental as I said the
model size has an effect not as much as
the model footprint itself but I mean
they sort of go hand in hand because
like the larger the model the slower
it's going to be on the next token and
next token and so on so they add up but
fundamentally when you look at the
bottleneck it is the size of the model
that defines the compute footprint that
you need right so to bring it to life
that would mean an slm would have a
smaller computation footprint or that's
not necessarily the case No Yeah by
definition it would if we're defining
slm as a certain parameter threshold
almost always will have a smaller
footprint in terms of compute and just
to give you comparison it's probably you
know if we compare the 10 billion
parameter model that I talked about
versus something like a 175 billion
parameter you know we're talking about
two orders of magnitude difference in
terms of actual speed right everything
is not again things are not linear
actually can you provide a comparison of
the training data size is typically used
for slms compared to
llms practically speaking let me Define
different training strategies actually
for slm so what we call as training from
scratch wherein you know you're
essentially your model parameters right
I mean think about model parameters is
this giant Matrix and this Matrix
everything starts with zero because you
you haven't learned anything or you're
starting with this you know zero State
and then you give them certain amount of
data and then you start training so that
is that let's call it zero8 training
that's one approach of training small
language models the other approach is
you can take like a big model and then
you can actually go through different
techniques like pruning where you take
certain parameters out or you can
distill it which I can dive later or you
can quantize it which means that I can
go from a Precision of 32 bits to 8 Bits
or four bits right so I can actually
take this you know 100 billion parameter
model which would be 400 gigs and you
know if I chop it by four technically
you know it becomes a 25 billion
parameter model because that's the
amount of compute I would need so there
are different strategies in actually
creating these small language models now
to the question of training data larger
the model the hungrier it is and the
more data you need to feed the smaller
the model you can get away with smaller
amounts of data as well but it doesn't
mean that
the actual end result is going to be the
same in terms of accuracy and so on and
what we find practically is given a sort
of a fixed amount of data the larger the
model it's likely to do better and the
more data you actually feed into any
kind of model the more likely it is to
do better as well so the models are
actually very hungry for data and good
data and you get to train but I'll talk
about the next step which is rather than
using the slms or training the slms from
scratch fine-tuning these llms what that
means is instead of the zero weights
that I talked about earlier we actually
use a base model right like a model that
has already trained on a certain number
of training data but then the idea is
steering the model to a very specific
task now this task can be building a
financial analyst or an actual you know
in the case of know Healthcare like you
can build like healthcare models in case
of flip AI we built models to understand
observability data right so you can fine
tune and build these models so now to
give you some real examples right like
let's take some of the most popular you
know open source models where Lama 3 is
the most popular open source model out
there and that's trained on 14 trillion
tokens of data right like it's seen so
much data already ready but by no means
it is a expert in healthcare or in
observability and so on what we can do
is train on top of these models using
the data that we have curated and if you
look at meditron which was a healthcare
model they train on roughly 50 billion
tokens of data Bloomberg trained a
financial analyst model and that was
again you know in the hundreds of
billions of tokens and we have trained
our models with like 100 billion tokens
of data now that's sort of the contrast
right like we're talking about two
orders of magnitude less data than what
llms would need only reason this is
possible is by using those base models
but the specialization part you don't
require as much data as the
generalization number of tokens all
right got it and how do you ensure that
slms maintain fairness and avoid domain
specific biases because as are by the
nature very specialized for a specific
domain yeah very good question actually
it's a double it sword because on the
one hand when you talk about expert
models you do want them biased on the
topic right when I when I talk about
credit in the context of Finance it
means certain thing and credit can mean
something else in you know a different
context so you you sort of wanted bias
towards your domain in any ways so
that's how I think about bias in terms
of functional capability but you know
let's talk about bias in terms of
anything that is taking action right
like in terms of like now if the same
model is being used to actually pass a
loan or determine who needs a loan or
not that's a different kind of bias
right like that is more inherent of a
decision-making bias and that actually
comes with data discipline what you need
to do is you need to train the model or
ensure the model has data on all the
pragmatic things that you're likely to
actually see in the real world what that
means is if the model is being trained
to make decisions on offering loans we
need to make sure that under represented
people in society are actually being
trained in the model so you know the
model like if the model is only seen a
certain demographic while training it's
going to say no to people who have not
represented in that training data so
that curation of training data and
evaluation data I like to say this is
the evaluation data or your test data is
is far more important right like that
needs to be extremely thorough and a
reflection of what is out there in the
real world so you know that whatever
number you get is close to the number
that happens when you deploy there's so
many blogs so many people I talk to
everybody's concern as hey my test data
says 90% accurate when I deploy I only
see like 60 70% accuracy because you
know people didn't spend the right
amount of time in curating the right
training data and more importantly the
right evaluation data to make sure the
biases are taken care of or reflected
that you would encounter in the real
world so to me it boils down to good
data practices and good evaluation
practices for the benefit of our
listeners can you explain the difference
between curation data and evaluation
data yeah yeah so when I say training
data this is the model these are the
examples that the model sees throughout
its training process so the evaluation
or test data is what we call as a
heldout data set as a this data is never
shown to the model for training so it
doesn't know that this data exists it is
only shown during inference and by
inference inference is a process where
the model doesn't memorize anything it
is a static process everything is Frozen
the model is Frozen at that time it does
not learn with that example
it just sees the data gives you an
output and done it doesn't complete the
feedback loop of if that was correct or
wrong got it so to ensure that we don't
have unwanted biases it's important to
ensure that we have curation data and
evaluation data which are fit for
purpose yeah so again curation I call it
a training data right like curation
would be the process so your training
data is what the examples that the model
will see and the test data is what the
model will never see during the training
process and you know just to add more
color here we have really good
organizations follow the complete blind
process of training or annotating data
right what that means is you would give
the same example to many people and they
don't know what they labeling and you
may actually repeat labeling of the data
Etc so you actually create this process
where you are creating this training
data a diverse set of training data that
is being labeled by multiple people and
you can also ensure that the people who
are labeling this data are not from a
single demographic you're actually
taking a slice of real life demographics
into account so you're getting like
diversity all around so you're ensuring
that the biases don't creep through in
your process so I would say 95% of
mitigating bias is actually to do with
how you curate your training data and
evaluation data got it what about
hallucinations in slms compared to llms
yeah um so llms by Nature um as I said
they are general purpose in in nature so
they know as much about Napoleon as much
as like other topics like how to write a
good program in Python right like so
it's this extreme thing and that comes
with burden so now let's go back to this
whole inference process that I talked
about right like the model is predicting
this one token at a time and now imagine
for some reason let's say somebody
decided to name their variable Napoleon
right and Napoleon predicted the
variable as Napoleon and suddenly the
model with the context of Napoleon
things like oh this must be a history
and it goes off and writes about we ask
to develop a program but it has actually
written some something about Napoleon
right po are opposites in terms of
output and that's actually what
hallucination that's where it comes from
which is it is actually an unsure the
model is unsure as to okay which path it
needs to go down to synthesize the
output for the question you've asked and
by Nature with slms there's less things
for it to think about so that the space
that it needs to like think from is
reduced the second is because it is
drained on a lot of coding data and so
on
even when say Napoleon may come in as a
decoded token unlikely that the model is
going to Veer into history topic because
majority of the time the model has spent
learning is only on coding so it's going
to assume that's a variable and decode
right so that's of the advantage of slm
because it's an expert it doesn't know
anything else so it's going to focus on
just that topic or its expertise rather
than think so typic Al an order of
magnitude difference in hallucination
rates when you think about a
well-trained slm versus an llm right do
you have any real world example of a any
challenging problem which has been
solved more efficiently with slms rather
than llms interesting question and I'll
give you it's going to be a long answer
so I think we'll go through a bunch of
examples I would say traditionally
speaking you know if you had the same
amount of data and you want use an slm
versus an llm look llm is more likely to
win just because of the power the more
parameters gives you more flexibility
more creativity and so on that's going
to win but the reason why you train an
slm is for more controllability
deployment cost accuracy that kind of
reasons and and happy to dive into that
as well so traditionally speaking that
has been the the norm that is starting
to change a bit if I look at examples of
something like in healthcare a couple
examples like
meditron these are open- Source
Healthcare models that they have trained
and when I look at if I recall the
numbers they had their version one which
was like a couple of years ago even like
their 70 billion model was actually
outperforming a 540 billion model by
Google Google had trained like these
models called Palm which were you know
Healthcare specific right so merron and
they recently retrained the models on
Lama 3 8 billion and that actually beats
their own model which is 70 billion from
the previous year so if you sort of
compare in a timeline of this 540
billion parameter model from Google
which was like a general purpose sort of
healthcare model versus a more specific
Healthcare slm by meditron and then an
slm version two by them it's like a 10x
Improvement that has you know happened
in the last two and a half years right
so I would say and if I recall even
their hallucination rates are a lot less
compared to what Google had and that's
one example another example I would say
is again in the healthcare space it's a
radiology oncology report model I think
it's called rad GPT or rad oncology GPT
and that was the output I remember was
something like the Llama models would be
at equivalent of 1% accuracy and these
models were at 60 70% accuracy right
that dramatic a jump that actually
relates to training data and happy to
dive in a little more so now you see
that difference right like of like
really large models and that's because
when you think about the general purpose
models they have never seen like
Radiology oncology that kind of reports
or data like that doesn't exist on the
internet and now you have a model that
is trained on these data that is very
constrained to an organization
and you start to see this amazing almost
crazy 1% versus 60% accuracy result and
improvements so I would say you know
there are these examples where the data
sets are very constrained to the
environment that you operate in that
gives the slm's advantage and then
something that is practical so something
that is like open in the world so
hopefully I'm happy to double click I
know I've talked a lot here now good
examples that's a really big difference
from 1% to 60 to 70% Improvement in
terms of identifying or inference yeah
actually I have something more to add
there something this this is like heart
off the press just a couple of hours ago
there's a model series called Deep seek
R1 that just launched and deep seek it's
actually a if I forget maybe five
somewhere around like 600 billion
parameter model but it's a mixture of
expert model so activation parameters
that I earlier talked about that's only
about 32 or 35 billion parameters so
almost like 20x reduction in size you
know when you practically talk in terms
of the amount of compute and that model
is actually outperforming the latest of
open AI 01 03 series models and CLA from
anthropic and so on right and it's
pretty insane like when you think about
again we don't know the size of say clae
3 .5 or GPT 40 they don't publish it but
we do know those are probably in the
hundreds of billions of parameters but
for a model that is effectively 35
billion parameters of activated size to
actually be better than these models is
just insane and I think it deals again
it deals with like how they train Etc
and so on but I think it comes back to
the question of the mixture of expert
model when you take a bunch of small
models and put them together they're
likely to as we see these numbers
they're likely to perform better than
like a huge model that has this one sort
of giant computational footprint end to
end I do think this is a sign of more
things to come where slms or collection
of slms are actually going to be way
better than a single 1 trillion
parameter or a 10 trillion parameter
model that's where I would bet
interesting times I'd like to move to
the next topic which is around
Enterprise ad option if you can tell us
about a time when you gave specific
advice to an Enterprise deciding between
slms and llms and what was the process
what questions did you asked them and
how did you help them decide yeah I'd
say Enterprise is a very interesting
case and and by definition Enterprise
has data that nobody's ever seen it's
not the data that is very very unique to
them so I say like Enterprises have a
last mile problem and this last mile
problem manifests in two ways is one is
the data manifestation which is the lack
of the model has never probably seen the
data that you know you have in your
Enterprise it better not right like
because you have security guard rails in
terms of like data and so on the second
is actually making this model practical
and deployed in your environment so
tackling the first part of it which is
data right because the model has never
seen your data you need to fine tune the
data on your own Enterprise Data Corpus
so getting clean data right like that's
my first advice is getting clean data so
sort of advice them on how to produce
this good data and then the second is
evaluation data right how do you to my
earlier examples right like I have
people who say like hey I had 90%
accuracy on my test set but when I
deploy I only see 60% or 70% accuracy
because your test set wasn't
representative of what you actually get
in the real world and then you need to
think about how to deploy the model
because there's a cost associated with
it so when you're sort of thinking
through slms you're always there's a
trade-off that you're always trying to
do which is accuracy versus cost right
and then that becomes sort of like your
main optimization point right like you
don't want something that is cheap and
does no work or you don't want something
that is really good but it's too
expensive for you to justify bringing it
in so finding that sweet spot is what I
think is like extremely important for
Enterprises to do I would say these are
my general advice on how to sort of
think through deploying in the
Enterprise deploying slms in the
Enterprise and do you have any stories
around the challenges faced by
Enterprises when they adopted slms how
did they overcome it yeah I think as we
look through many of these open- Source
models that companies try to bring
inhouse because the model has never seen
the data things keep changing there are
two reasons one is you didn't train well
or you didn't evaluate well so you
didn't get a hold of the model the
second is the underlying sort of data
and what you get and how people use your
product keeps changing over time so
there's a drift in terms of you're not
able to capture all the use cases at a
given static time point and then as time
goes along you have people using your
product or technology in a different way
and you need to keep evolving right so
again comes back to how you curate your
data how can you actually train well and
then iterate on the model right so you
need to actually bring in observability
into your model which means that when
the models are failing you're capturing
that when a user is not happy about a
certain output you're capturing that the
why somebody was not happy you're
capturing those aspects so bringing all
of this in and then iterating on the
model there's also one thing which we
haven't talked about especially in the
Enterprise like you know we talked a lot
about fine-tuning the other approach is
called retrieval augmented generation or
rag which is more commonly used so what
happens is when you bring a model in it
doesn't have it's never seen your data
and what you can do is certain
terminologies or Technologies or
something jargons or something specific
that you have let's say in your company
wiki page or or some sort of text spec
that you've written you can actually
give the model a utility to say hey when
somebody asks a question on this
retrieve this information from this
Wikipedia or this indexed uh storage
that you can bring in as more context
because you never seen you don't
understand that data and you can use
that as context to predict what the user
are asked for right so your augment ing
the existing base model so typically
people like approach in two different
ways as they deploy so either you fine
tune which I talked about earlier or you
can use retrieval augmented generation
to get better results and it's a pretty
interesting there's a people that debate
rag is better than fine tuning or fine
tuning is better than rag that's a topic
we can dive in if you're interested
maybe for another day we'll stick to the
Enterprise theme and digging a bit
deeper into the challenges so what are
the common challenges Enterprises face
not only in bringing the models in but
also training them but also from a
deployment perspective yeah let me talk
about deployment first and it's actually
underrated like people focus on the
training part people don't think about
the pragmatic aspect right so one is how
do you determine the right footprint of
the resources that you need right like
the right kind of gpus because your
model can fit on multiple gpus but
there's a cost performance tradeoff
right like so if you take the really
huge GPU and you're underutilizing it
that's not actually practical right like
you're not going to get budget for that
so you have this sort of becomes like
this three axis rather than two axis so
the x axis you can think about the cost
Y axis you can think about performance
or latency and the z-axis you can think
about accuracy so you're now trying to
optim I in these three axes to find this
sweet spot that oh well I have budget
approved for X number of dollars and I
need a minimum of this accuracy what is
the trade-off I can make in terms of
well if somebody gets the answer in 200
milliseconds versus 100 milliseconds
that's acceptable right so you start to
like figure out this tradeoff that you
can have to select the best sort of
optimal setting that you can go Deploy
on now that requ requires you to have
expertise in multiple things right it
means that you need to know the model
deployment Frameworks or the underlying
tools like tensor flow py torch so those
things are specialized skills you need
to know how to pick the right gpus and
create this tradeoff or these trade-offs
that I talked about and then you need to
think about you know people are experts
in devops when it's say an organization
me experts in devops when it comes to
CPU and traditional workloads GPU
workloads are different right like now
you need to train people on how to
monitor gpus how to understand how to
the obsorb part comes in so all of that
needs to be sort of packaged and tackled
for you to deploy well on the Enterprise
I don't know if you want to double click
on anything in the deployment side maybe
just quickly if you can touch on what
are the key differences between
deploying or the tradeoffs between
deploying on Prem and on the cloud yeah
I don't know do you mean in the cloud do
you mean an API based service or yes
yeah I mean API Based Services there is
no difference in you using a payments
API versus an an ml API right like it is
as long as you can make a rest call you
can actually use them which makes them
extremely simple but if you're deploying
on Prem what I would say is I'll make it
more generic if deploying in your VPC
then that comes with all the importance
that I talked about right with the
addition of compliance and data
governance right so because you want to
deploy it in the right sort of framework
another example like flip AI actually we
support our deployments in two modes
which is you can deploy as a SAS or you
can actually Deploy on Prem in this on
Prem version are it's completely air
gapped we actually we have scripts
whether it is like cloud native scripts
or terraforms and Helm charts and so on
so we make it easy for our customers to
go deploy this basically with one click
because everything is automated in terms
of bringing up the infrastructure and so
on but in order to enable that we have
done those benchmarks those cost
accuracy performance sort of tradeoffs
all of that we have packaged it we've
written a little bit about that in our
blogs and this is what an Enterprise
adopting any slm would need to do
themselves as well but that comes with
fa bit of investment because it is not
commoditized yet in terms of deploying
llms in house or slms as well yeah but
if you pick on that flip. a example what
drives a customer to pick up either the
SAS model or the on-prem model what are
they looking for or what do they gain
when they go for on Prem or for the SAS
one yeah we work with highly regulated
Industries where the customer data needs
to be not processed by any third party
and that cannot leave their security
boundaries right so it's primarily
driven by compliance and data governance
there's another thing which is again
applies to flip AI but also applies to a
lot of Enterprise adoption which I
didn't talk about is robustness so when
you rely on robustness and slas and slos
when you rely on like a third party API
even open AI or Claud anthropic or any
of those they don't give you SLA they
don't tell you like hey my request is
going to finish in X number of seconds
they don't give you availability
guarantees and so on so as an Enterprise
think about an Enterprise who's building
a five 9es availability or even higher
nines of availability now they have no
control over nobody is promising them
right like if you're using a SAS service
nobody's promising them X number of
whether it is accuracy or even the nines
of availability that they need but
bringing inhouse and deploying with best
practice I es and redundancy and all of
this you can actually guarantee certain
level of availability as far as these
models come and then the robustness part
right these models tend to hallucinate
less right like if you're using an API
based service which is a more general
purpose model you cannot have these kind
of hallucination rates because your
performance is going to degrade
hallucination would be a factor for on
Prem and SAS right that would be the
same well it can be because in terms of
general purpose models but if the same
model was available for SAS or on Prem
yes then there's equivalency there the
other is in-house expertise if a
customer doesn't have in-house expertise
of managing or they don't want to take
out that burden then they end up going
SAS versus going on pram the other
factor which is a general factor I would
say is going is availability or this
this is more of a I take that back it's
I was going to talk about llm slms but
if the same model being SAS or on Prem
it basically comes down to compliance
data governance the robustness aspect
and being inhouse expertise and the
availability guarantees that you can
give it typically comes down to these
factors got it compliance availability
inhouse expertise you touched on a few
key skills that are required for
deployment so you touched on model
deployment framework you touched on the
knowledge about GPU and and also about
how do you observe the workload on GPU
what are the other skills that or
knowledge areas that Engineers should
focus on to effectively build and deploy
slms I think those factors I talked
about should cover most of them and I
would suggest if somebody is wants to
try and get their hands like you know
try deploying a model locally on your
laptop there are even these you can you
know with the latest Hardwares and stuff
like you can easily deploy a billion
parameter model on your laptop so I
would actually kick tires taking these
models well you don't need a 1 billion
parameter you can even go with a 100
million parameter model to sort of like
have a idea of what it takes so you will
get some expertise in diving into these
Frameworks right like deployment
Frameworks and model Frameworks and then
you'll sort of get an idea about you
know as you run benchmarks on say
different kinds of Hardware you get a
little bit of idea on those trade-offs
right that I talked about ultimately
what you're trying to build is this axis
that I talked about like accuracy
performance and cost so that is a more
pragmatic take I would do is start on
your laptop or a small instance you can
get on the cloud KCK the tires and then
that really builds that experience
because with sort of devops and other
sort of Technologies I feel like the
more you read the more you get confused
and you can sort of condense that
Knowledge Learning by actually just
doing it agreed I want to talk about
move on to the next theme which is
around architectural and Technical
differences or distinctions of slms but
I think we have covered quite a few of
those already which is around training
data around the tradeoffs of model size
and accuracy but maybe a few bits so
what are the main security
vulnerabilities in slms and how can they
be mitigated I think practically
speaking speaking you know security
vulnerabilities are not specific to slms
or llms they're not one has better over
the other I don't think that that's the
right framework to think about okay I
think security vulnerabilities exist in
any sort of language models they
manifest in slightly different way what
I mean by that is you're either trying
to retrieve data that the model is seen
right so you're actually tricking the
model to give some data in the hope that
it has seen some pii data or something
of interest it's not going to tell you
so you're trying to exfiltrate that data
out or the other is actually behavior
modification right like you are you're
sort of injecting it's sort of equal to
SQL injection right like where you're
are trying to get the database to do
something by injecting something that is
malicious the same way you would do that
in the prompt and trick the model to do
something different and give you the
data so those are the typical
security vulnerabilities I would say
that people tend to exploit but they're
not exclusive to an slm or an llm it
happens in both right and what are the
key architectural differences between
slms and llms and is there any
fundamental design philosophy which is
different not really the same technique
that you use to train a 10 billion
parameter model can be done for a 100
billion or a 1 trillion architecturally
they aren't different or neither are the
training techniques techniques I would
say well people do employ different
techniques it doesn't mean that the
techniques are not going to work on llms
as well right like so it's just a size
equation but what is interesting is how
these slms get created they can be
trained from scratch or fine-tune but
you can take an llm and make them an slm
and that's a very interesting topic so
couple of most common things that people
do is quantization and distillation MH
quantization is where you actually take
take a large model and you convert the
model parameters and this can be done
like statically it doesn't even need a
whole process what you're basically
doing is chopping off the bits you take
a 32 bit precision and you make it a
16bit Precision or you can make a 8 bit
precision and you're done right like
you're basically changing the Precision
of those floats in your model weights
and you're done now distillation is
actually a very interesting and there
are different kinds of technique
distillation
at a high level is where you take a
large model and you take the outputs of
those large models and use that to train
a small model so what that means is it's
sort of a teacher student relationship
the teacher model that knows a lot and
can produce high quality data which a
small model just can't because it has
creativity limitations and because the
number of parameters are fewer so you
take this large model you generate a lot
of output from that and you use that to
then trade Trin your small language
model which then can see equivalent
performances and there a lot of examples
actually of this so if we look at the
you know what I talked about the medron
even like the models called as open bio
you know even multilingual models like
what I've seen there was this Taiwanese
Mandarin model again like they used like
really large models took a lot of data
and then trained and the model was doing
better than like gp4 and Claw Etc all
because it was trained through
distillation and so on that's a really
practical approach and a lot of fine
tuning happens through distillation
which is generate the data and then
there can be a more complex version of
distillation where you're training both
models in tandem so to speak and you're
taking the signals that the larger model
learns and giving that to the smaller
model to adapt so they're very complex
ways of training and distillation as
well okay so distillation is the teacher
student model brings it to life you can
intuitively understand that M whereas
quantization is taking a large model and
chopping of pets I'm struggling to
understand that how does that make it
specific to a domain or is this not
related to a domain no it doesn't it
does not it just makes it smaller for
you to deploy and manage right so it's
more of a cost performance tradeoff cost
performance accuracy tradeoff it doesn't
make you like an expert model by any me
means so it's still a general purpose
model correct correct but what we see
and there's a lot of trend is let's say
I train a model with x amount of data a
10 billion parameter model versus 100
billion parameter model and then
quantize it there's a lot of examples
where taking 100 billion parameter model
and reducing it quantizing it to the
size of your 10 billion parameter model
versus training one you could get better
results so it's the same purpose same
data except you train a larger model and
then you quantize it so there are people
have done that with a lot of success
right you also briefly mentioned about
model pruning and when we discussed
about the differentiation between slm
and llm attributes can you expand on
what pruning is and how does that work
yeah so when I talk about 10 so one
thing we have to understand
fundamentally is when I say 10 billion
parameters it doesn't mean that 10
billion parameters are all storing good
amount of data they're all needed
equally to produce the result and this
is actually analogous to the human brain
like it is predicted that the human
brain only uses 13% of its entire
capacity right like the other 87% is
just there so same way these models are
sparse in nature by sparse I mean the
best way to understand is remember when
I talked about these Matrix having zero
weights and as you train a model like
these numbers change right like these
numbers change and let's say they
increment you've learned something the
that parameter is nonzero so when you
actually look at a train model it
doesn't mean that all the models have
gone all the parameters have gone from
zero to something meaningful like there
are still a lot of parameters that are
close to zero so those don't necessarily
add anything meaningful to your ultimate
output so you can start to prune those
models again I'm trying to explain
practically there is more Nuance to this
but effectively that's what's happening
you're just removing those parts of the
model that have not been activated or
don't contribute in activation is you
run inference so now suddenly a 10
billion parameter model can be pruned to
like a 3 billion parameter model by
doing that that's the general idea of
pruning but I would say pruning is
become extremely less common as a
strategy these days rather mixture of
experts as I talked initially in the
podcast that's a more pragmatic way in
which the model itself is sort of
creating these specialized paths right
like in your training process you have a
huge model let's say 10 billion
parameter model but you're creating
these experts and the experts are
actually defining these paths that are
history expert math expert coding expert
and so on right like so these
effectively sort of utilizing the space
better while you train so that's more of
a state in which we are moving not to
say you cannot prune mixture of expert
model and so on but it's less common
that people do that and a factor of that
is how much efficient and faster gpus
and the underlying Frameworks have
become that you don't necessarily need
to bother with pruning all right we have
covered a lot of ground over here we
have covered the basics in terms of
water slms we have looked at the slm
attributes compared to llms we have
looked at Enterprise adoption and also
looked at architecture technical
distinctions and the training
differences between slms and llms as we
wrap up just a final couple of questions
sunel what emerging research area are
you most excited about for advancing
slms love this question you know I'll
talk about few things that people have
worked on and something that exciting
that is emerging as well speed is
actually a very important thing right
like when you think about vast number of
applications that are exist on the
Internet or people use speed is key
right like just because somebody
something is AI powered you're not going
to say like oh you can give me the
response in 60 minutes or 60 seconds
right like people still want fast so
people have spent a lot of time on
inference and making inference faster so
a big emerging research area is how to
scale things at inference there's a
technique that people have sort of
developed it's called speculative
decoding now this is very similar to
people who understand like compilers and
so on you know how you have a
speculative branching where you know
you're trying to guess where the code is
going to jump next and so on so same way
in inference while predicting the
current token you're also trying to get
the next token in a speculative manner
so you're basically in a single pass
you're producing multiple tokens right
like which means now you can actually
take like half the amount of time or 25%
of the time it would take to produce the
entire inference but again it's
speculative right which means the
accuracy takes a bit of hit but you
getting faster inference so that is a
very very exciting area the others I
would say like a lot of work has been
done on on device how to deploy these
slms on your laptop on your Raspberry Pi
that's an extremely exciting area
privacy preserving way of deploying
these llms that's a pretty active area
and exciting for me I'll keep the most
exciting is a couple of things I would
say which has started in the last maybe
six months since the 01 series of models
that open AI released which are where
the model actually is thinking based on
its own outputs now the best way to
actually explain this is you know how
you probably worked out math problems in
school where you know you have a rough
sheet on the right hand side you're
actually doing the nitty-gritty details
and then you're bringing that into
substituting into your equations and so
on so you have this scratch Pad of a lot
of thoughts and lot of rough work that
you're using to actually bring into your
answer the same way what is happening is
these models mods are generating all
these intermediate outputs and ideas and
things that it can actually use to
generate the final output and that is
super exciting because we starting to
see high accuracy in a lot of really
complex task but on the flip side it is
actually something that used to take us
like 5 seconds for inference is starting
to take 5 minutes right or 15 minutes
and so on because you're starting to
generate a lot of these intermediate
outputs or tokens that the model has to
use now this whole entire Paradigm is
called inference time scaling now the
larger the model you can imagine the
more time it takes to generate these
tokens the more compute footprint and so
on the smaller the model you can do it
faster and which is why I was talking
about all these faster inference etc
those actually start to come into
picture because now you can generate
these tokens in a faster Manner and you
can actually start to use them to get
higher accuracy at the end so inference
time scaling is a extremely exciting
area there are a lot of Open Source
models now that have come out that are
able to support this second is which is
again like fresh off the press there has
been a lot of speculation on using
reinforcement learning to train the
models from scratch so typically
speaking in a training process
reinforcement learning has been used so
just to explain the training process we
do what is called as pre-training where
the model learns on self-supervised data
and then we can talk about instruction
tuning where the model is giv certain
instructions or human curated data they
train that and then there's
reinforcement learning where the model
is given reinforcement learning signals
to well I prefer the output in a certain
way or you give signals to the model and
you train using that mhm but
reinforcement learning was never used to
train a model from scratch people
speculated it and so on but with this
deep seek R1 model they've actually used
reinforcement learning to train from
scratch that's a whole new that opens up
a whole new possibilities of on how you
would train this is completely new I'm
yet to read the entire paper you know
just as I said it released a couple
hours ago and I skimmed through it and
it's been always speculated but they
have actually put into research paper
and they've actually produced the
results so to me this is going to open
up a whole new way of how people train
these models and reinforcement learning
is really good at finding hacks on its
own so I wouldn't be surprised where it
is going to actually you know reduce the
model size and actually have a material
impact on these slms being even better
I'm extremely excited with these things
exciting space so you have spoken about
speculative decoding on device
deployment inference time scaling and
using reinforcement learning to train
from scratch quite a few emerging areas
before we close was there anything we
missed that you'd like to mention yeah
maybe I can bring through a practical
example like that I have been working on
for 3 years and putting all the things
that I've talked about together so at
flip AI you know we really an Enterprise
first company and we wanted the model to
be practical in all of the these
trade-offs that I mentioned and Deploy
on Prem or SAS whatever option our
customers wanted to choose we wanted to
give the customer the flexibility and
all the data governance aspect and as we
train these models right we didn't have
any of the llms that had capability of
doing anything in the observability data
space and this observability data is
sort of very tuned to what a company has
right you don't necessarily have this
data out in the wild so what we did is
to train these models we used like many
of the techniques that I talked through
this this podcast first we actually do
pre-training so we collect a lot of data
from the internet in terms of like say
stack Overflow logs that are available
Etc and then we put them to a rigorous
data cleaning pipeline because you need
really high quality data so we spend a
lot of time there to get really high
quality data but there's only so much
data that's available right like so we
actually curate uh data that are human
labeled and we also do synthetic data
generation you know similar to that
distillation process that I talked about
earlier and then finally you know what I
like to say is you know the model
actually trains and gets really good but
doesn't have practical knowledge and to
gain practical knowledge what we do is
we have created this gym I call this
this chaos gym maybe we have an internal
code name called otashi and if you're of
South Indian native speaker of any of
those languages you will appreciate
which basically means chaos and the idea
is this chaos framework goes and breaks
all these things and the flip model
predicts the output and then we use
reinforcement learning to align the
model better on hey you made a mistake
here or hey that's good you predicted it
correctly and then it goes and improves
the model so all these techniques
there's no one answer that gives you
performance out of your slms you have to
use a mix of these techniques to bring
all of this together so whoever is
building Enterprise grade slms I would
advise them to think in similar manner
we've actually got a paper as well that
is out you can check it on our website
that walks us through all of these
techniques that we've used and so on
overall I would say I remain bullish on
the slms because those are practical in
how Enterprises can actually bring and
give utility to their end customers and
llms don't necessarily give them that
Flex flexibility all the time and
especially in a regulated environment
llms are just not a option I'll make
sure we link to that paper in our show
notes thank you s for coming on the show
it's been a real pleasure this is Brides
Aman for software engineering radio
thank you for
listening thanks for listening to SC
radio an educational program brought to
you by It software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at se-
radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack Channel at seo.
slack.com you can also email us at team
e-r. this and all other episodes of SC
radio is licensed under Creative Commons
license
2.5 thanks for listening